Guide to the CBEN-ICON Kristen Kulinowski academic papers UA 198
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
CBEN-ICON Kristen Kulinowski academic papers
1993-2008
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Kulinowski, Kristen, Dr.
UA 198
6 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
CBEN-ICON Kristen Kulinowski academic papers contain records of the Center for Biological and Environmnetal Nanotechnology (CBEN) and the International Council on Nanotechnology (ICON) from roughly 2004 to 2008. Kulinowski was executive director of CBEN and director of ICON. This collection consists of six boxes of mixed media, including text, correspondence, publications, brochures and multimedia formats, such as DVDs. Subjects include the administrative side of CBEN and ICON, work with the National Science Foundation (NSF) and the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), and numerous conferences and workshops. The materials measure 6 linear feet (6 boxes).
Biographical Note
Vicki Colvin
Kenneth S. Pitzer-Schlumberger Professor Emeritus of Chemistry
Research Statement Professor Colvin's research explores how nanoscale particles interact with the environment and living systems. Her research draws on both synthetic chemistry for the preparation and control of novel nanophase systems as well as physical chemistry for the investigation of their unusual behavior. Currently her projects draw on the unique and responsive behavior of nanoparticles to solve problems related to water purification and targeted cell death.
[The following biographical materials were retrieved on August 12, 2009 from http://chem.rice.edu/FacultyDetail.cfm?RiceID=602]
Biographical Note
Kristen Kulinowski Faculty Fellow in Chemistry
Dr. Kulinowski is a Faculty Fellow in the Department of Chemistry at Rice University and Director for External Affairs for the Center for Biological and Environmental Nanotechnology (CBEN). She currently serves as the Director of the International Council on Nanotechnology (ICON), an international, multi-stakeholder organization whose mission is to develop and communicate information regarding potential environmental and health risks of nanotechnology thereby fostering risk reduction while maximizing societal benefit. She has experience as a chemical researcher, educator, curriculum developer, administrator, outreach coordinator and policy fellow.
Since 2004, Dr. Kulinowski has been actively engaged in developing and promoting the International Council on Nanotechnology (ICON) which provides a neutral forum in which experts from academia, governments, industry and nonprofit organizations can explore questions of nanotechnology's impact on environment, health and safety (EHS). She directed an effort that resulted in the web publication of the first publicly available database of citations to peer-reviewed papers on nano EHS. Other activities of ICON include a survey of best practices for nanomaterial handling in the workplace and a public portal of information on nanotechnology EHS.
Dr. Kulinowski has extensive experience in science education, particularly in developing innovative curricula at the undergraduate level, and developed Rice¿s first introductory undergraduate course on nanotechnology. From 2002-2004 Dr. Kulinowski served as CBEN Executive Director for Education, developing and managing an educational outreach portfolio of programs for audiences that range from middle school children to adults. During this time the center established itself as a national leader in nanotechnology educational outreach.
Prior to joining CBEN, she was a lecturer in chemistry at Cal Poly (San Luis Obispo) for three years and came to Rice as an instructor in chemistry in 1998. In 2001 she was selected by the Optical Society of America and SPIE-The International Society for Optical Engineering as their Congressional Science Fellow and worked in the D.C. office of a member of the U.S. House of Representatives on issues including weapons of mass destruction, anti-terrorism legislation and domestic nuclear power security. She was instrumental in shepherding through new legislation on the stockpiling of potassium iodide near nuclear power plants. As a longtime volunteer with American Red Cross Disaster Relief Services, Dr. Kulinowski brought food and water to rescue workers at the Pentagon on September 11, 2001.
Dr. Kulinowski is highly sought after as a speaker and has given invited talks on issues of nanotechnology environmental health and safety and science policy throughout the US, Europe and the Middle East. She has consulted with governments and governmental advisory bodies regarding responsible nanotechnology, and serves as chair of the ASTM International Subcommittee E56.03 on Environment, Health and Safety. Dr. Kulinowski earned a B.S. in chemistry at Canisius College and her M.S. and Ph.D. in chemistry at the University of Rochester.
Selected Publications Kulinowski, K.M. and V.L. Colvin "Backgrounder on nanoparticles and amyloid diseases." Virtual Journal of Nanotechnology Environment, Health & Safety, April (2007).
Colvin, V.L. and K.M. Kulinowski "Nanoparticles as catalysts for protein fibrillation." PNAS (2007): 0703194104.
Kulinowski, K.M., D.R. Johnson, and J. Baker "Nanotechnology & environmental professionals." EnviroMentor, 6(3) (2007).
Kulinowski, K.M. "The International Council on Nanotechnology: A new model of engagement, in Nanoscale: Issues and Perspectives for the Nano Century." (2007).
"A role for all, with aid from government." The Environmental Forum, July/August (2005): 45.
Kulinowski, Kristen M. "Nanotechnology: From "Wow" to "Yuck"?." Bulletin of Science, Technology and Society, 24 (2004): 13-20.
Kulinowski, K.M., et al. "Porous metals from colloidal templates." Advanced Materials, 12(11) (2000): 833-838.
Kulinowski, K.M. "Incorporating nanotechnology into K-12 education, in Nanotechnology: Societal implications II Individual perspectives.": 322-327.
Kulinowski, Kristen M.; Colvin, Vicki L. "The Environmental Impact of Engineered Nanomaterials." .(In Press)
Presentations "Nanotechnology: The Science Behind the News." American Bar Association Quick Teleconference,. (January 2007)
"An Update on Nanotechnology." Houston Bar Association Environmental Section Luncheon Meeting,. (February 2008)
"Effective Office Visits." Science Education for New Civic Engagements and Responsibilities teleconference,. (March 2008)
"National Citizens Technology Forum on Human Enhancement, Identity & Biology." North Carolina State University web dialogue,. (March 2008)
"International Nano-EHS Research Needs Assessment." AAAS Southwest Regional Meeting, Albuquerque. (April 2008)
Awards
Congressional Science Fellowship, Optical Society of America and SPIE-The International Society for Optical Engineering. (9/01-8/02). [ The following biographical materials were retrieved on August 12, 2009 from http://chem.rice.edu/FacultyDetail.cfm?RiceID=1200 ]
Scope and Content
CBEN-ICON Kristen Kulinowski academic papers contain records of the Center for Biological and Environmnetal Nanotechnology (CBEN) and the International Council on Naotechnology (ICON) from roughly 2004 to 2008. Kulinowski was executive director of CBEN and director of ICON. This collection consists of six boxes of mixed media, including text, correspondence, publications, brochures and multimedia formats, such as DVDs. Subjects include the administrative side of CBEN and ICON, work with the National Science Foundation (NSF) and the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), and numerous conferences and workshops. The materials measure 6 linear feet (6 boxes) and are in good shape.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series.
Series I - Reference Papers Series II - ICON (International Council on Nanotechnology) Series III - CBEN (Center for Biological and Environmental Nanotechnology) Series IV - Viki Colvin papers
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Nanotechnology; Environment
Document Types
publications
Places
Rice University
Subjects (Persons)
Colvin, Vicki, Dr.
- Series I: Reference papers [File 1.1 contains a list of topics for most of the reference files.], 49208
  - Reference files 1 - 48; 2001-2008. [File 1.1 contains a list of topics for most of the reference files.], 49206 (Box 1)
    Notes on box 1
    Topics include nanokids, workshops, risk reports, policy, undergraduate classes and professional organizations. [File 1.1 contains a list of topics for most of the reference files.]
  - Reference files 49-94; 2002-2005. Topics include professional organizations, CBEN papers, annual reports, proposals, courses, summer programs., 49207 (Box 2)
    Notes on Box 2
    Topics include professional organizations, CBEN papers, annual reports, proposals, courses, summer programs.
  - Reference files 96-113; 2004-2005, topics cover annual reports, professional and governmental organizations., 49214 (Box 3)
    Notes on Box 3
    Topics cover annual reports, professional and governmental organizations.
- Series II: ICON (International Council on Nanotechnology), 49209
  - ICON related materials: folders 18-31., 49210 (Box 3)
- Series III: CBEN (Center for Biological and Environmental Nanotechnology), 49211
  - CBEN: folder 32-44. Topics include NSF site visit, brocure, nanokids card game and video., 49212 (Box 3)
    Topics include NSF site visit, staff meetings, resumes and curriculum vitae, workshops, NSF grantees conference, annual reports.
  - CBEN papers: folders 1 - 6, Topics include NSF site visit, brochure, nanokids came and video., 49213 (Box 4)
    Notes on Box 4
    Topics include NSF site visit, brochure, nanokids card game and video.
- Series IV: Viki Colvin papers, 49215
  - Colvin papers: folders 7-36, Topics include toxicology programs, defense study group, National Research Council, professional meetings and organizations, articles and papers., 49216 (Box 4)
    Topics include toxicology programs, defense study group, National Research Council, professional meetings and organizations, articles and papers.
  - Colvin papers: folders 1-11, topics include papers and articles, proposals, committee meetings, baseline reviews, Rice faculty council., 58225 (Box 5)
- Series V: Kulinowski papers, 1993-2008; 58226
  - Kulinowski papers, folders 12-32. Topics inlude carbon toxicity report, EPA paper, journals, community based research, graduate courses and other materials., 58227 (Box 5)
  - Kulinowski papers, folders 1-40. Topics include conferences, published articles, environmental law, National Science Foundation, and other topics., 58228
- Series VI: Digital Files and ephemera, 1993-2008; 58222
  - Digital files and ephemera, envelopes 41-50, topics include Nanokids, ICON, CBEN, conferences adn professionla meetings, SPIE silk tie, Rice Univeristy chemistry department materials., 1993-2008; 58223 (Box 6, Envelope data_value_missing_f4d5c8a0e1f5d836828625a36048d01d)